This is a Galton Board.
Maybe you've seen one before. It's a popular demonstration
of how even when a single event is chaotic and random,
with an effectively unknowable outcome,
it's still possible to make precise statements about a large number of events,
namely how the relative proportions for many different outcomes are distributed.
More specifically, the Galton board illustrates one of the most prominent
distributions in all of probability, known as the Normal distribution,
more colloquially known as a Bell curve, and also called a Gaussian distribution.
There's a very specific function to describe this distribution.
Very pretty. We'll get into it later,
but right now, I just want to emphasize how the normal distribution is,
as the name suggests, very common. It shows up in a lot of seemingly unrelated contexts.
If you were to take a large number of people who sit in a similar demographic
and plot their heights, those heights tend to follow a normal distribution.
If you look at a large swath of very big natural numbers
and you ask how many distinct prime factors does each one of those numbers have,
the answers will very closely track with a certain normal distribution.
Now, our topic for today is one of the crown jewels in all of probability theory.
It's one of the key facts that explains why this distribution is as common as it is,
known as the Central Limit Theorem.
This lesson is meant to go back to the basics,
giving you the fundamentals on what the Central Limit Theorem is saying,
what normal distributions are, and I want to assume minimal background.
We're going to go decently deep into it, but after this,
I'd still like to go deeper and explain why the theorem is true,
why the function underlying the normal distribution
has the very specific form that it does,
why that formula has a pi in it,
and, most fun,
why those last two facts are actually more related than a lot of traditional explanations would suggest.
That second lesson is also meant to be the follow on to the convolutions video that I promised.
So, there's a lot of interrelated topics here.
But right now, back to the fundamentals.
I'd like to kick things off with an overly simplified model of the Galton board.
In this model, we will assume that each ball falls directly onto a certain central peg
and then it has a 50 - 50 probability of bouncing to the left or to the right,
and we'll think of each of those outcomes as either adding one or subtracting one from its position.
Once one of those is chosen, we make the highly unrealistic assumption that
it happens to land dead on in the middle of the peg adjacent below it, where again,
it'll be faced with the same 50 - 50 choice of bouncing to the left or to the right.
For the one I'm showing on screen, there are five different rows of pegs.
So our little hopping ball makes five different random choices between plus one and minus one,
and we can think of its final position as basically being the sum of all of those different numbers.
Which in this case happens to be one,
and we might label all of the different buckets with the sum that they represent.
As we repeat this, we're looking at different possible sums for those five random numbers.
And for those of you who are inclined to complain that this is a highly unrealistic model for the true Galton board
let me emphasize - the goal right now is not to accurately model physics,
the goal is to give a simple example to illustrate the central limit theorem,
and for that, idealized though this might be, it actually gives us a really good example.
If we let many different balls fall,
making yet another unrealistic assumption that they don't influence each other, as if they're all ghosts,
then the number of balls that fall into each different bucket
gives us some loose sense for how likely each one of those buckets is.
In this example the numbers are simple enough that it's not too hard to explicitly
calculate what the probability is for falling into each bucket.
If you do want to think that through, you'll find it very reminiscent of Pascal's triangle,
but the neat thing about our theorem is how far it goes beyond the simple examples.
So, to start off at least, rather than making explicit calculations,
let's just simulating things by running a large number of samples
and letting the total number of results in each different outcome
give us some sense for what that distribution looks like.
As I said, the one on screen has five rows,
so each sum that we're considering includes only five numbers.
The basic idea of the central limit theorem is that if you increase the size of that sum,
for example, here that would mean increasing the number of rows of pegs for each ball to bounce off
then the distribution that describes where that sum is going to fall
looks more and more like a bell curve.
Here, it's actually worth taking a moment to write down that general idea.
The setup is that we have a random variable and that's basically shorthand for a random
process where each outcome of that process is associated with some number.
We'll call that random number X.
For example, each bounce off the peg is a random process modeled with two outcomes.
Those outcomes are associated with the numbers negative one and positive one.
Another example of a random variable would be rolling a die,
where you have six different outcomes each one associated with a number.
What we're doing is taking multiple different samples of that variable and adding them all together.
On our Galton board, that looks like letting the ball bounce off
multiple different pegs on its way down to the bottom,
and in the case of a die, you might imagine
rolling many different dice and adding up the results.
The claim of the central limit theorem
is that as you let the size of that sum get bigger and bigger,
then the distribution of that sum, how likely it is to fall into different possible values,
will look more and more like a bell curve.
That's it, that is the general idea.
Over the course of this lesson, our job is to make that statement more quantitative.
We're going to put some numbers to it, put some formulas to it, show how you can use it to make predictions.
For example, here's the kind of question I want you to be able to answer by the end of this video:
suppose you roll the die 100 times, and you added together the results.
Could you find a range of values such that you're 95% sure that the sum will fall within that range.
Or maybe I should say, find the smallest possible range of values such that this is true.
The neat thing is, you'll be able to answer this question whether it's a fair die or if it's a weighted die.
Now, let me say at the top that this theorem has three different assumptions that go into it.
Three things that have to be true before the theorem follows
and I'm actually not going to tell you what they are until the very end of the video.
Instead, I want you to keep your eye out and see if you can notice and maybe predict
what those three assumptions are going to be.
As a next step to better illustrate just how general this theorem is,
I want to run a couple more simulations for you focused on the dice example.
Usually, if you think of rolling a die, you think of the six outcomes as being equally probable,
but the theorem actually doesn't care about that.
We could start with a weighted die
something with a non-trivial distribution across the outcomes
and the core idea still holds,
for the simulation what will do is take some distribution,
like this one that is skewed towards lower values.
I'm going to take 10 distinct samples from that distribution,
and then I'll record the sum of that sample on the plot, on the bottom.
Then I'm going to do this many many different times.
Always with the sum of size 10
but keep track of where those sums ended up to give us a sense of the distribution.
And in fact, let me rescale the y direction to give us room to run an even larger number of samples,
and I'll let it go all the way up to a couple thousand
and as it does, you'll notice that the shape that starts to emerge
looks like a bell curve.
Maybe if you squint your eyes you can see it skews a tiny bit to the left,
but it's neat that something so symmetric emerged from a starting point that was so asymmetric.
To better illustrate what the central limit theorem is all about,
let me run four of these simulations in parallel.
Where on the upper left I'm doing it - we're only adding two dice at a time.
On the upper right, we're doing it where we're adding five dice at a time,
the lower left is the one that we just saw, adding 10 dice at a time
and then we'll do another one with a bigger sum, 15 at a time.
Notice how on the upper left when we're just adding two dice,
the resulting distribution doesn't really look like a bell curve,
it looks a lot more reminiscent of the one we started with - skewed towards the left.
But as we allow for more and more dice in each sum,
the resulting shape that comes up in these distributions looks more and more symmetric.
It has the lump in the middle and fade towards the tail shape of a bell curve.
Let me emphasize again, you can start with any different distribution.
Here I'll run it again but where most of the probability is tied up in the numbers 1 and 6
with very low probability for the mid values.
Despite completely changing the distribution for an individual roll of the die,
it's still the case that a bell curve shape will emerge as we consider the different sums.
Illustrating things with a simulation like this is very fun
and it's kind of neat to see order emerge from chaos
but it also feels a little imprecise. Like in this case.
When I cut off the simulation at 3000 samples, even though it kind of looks like a bell curve,
the different buckets seem pretty spiky?
And you might wonder is it supposed to look that way
or is that just an artifact of the randomness in the simulation,
and if it is, how many samples do we need
before we can be sure that what we're looking at is representative of the true distribution?
Instead moving forward, let's get a little more theoretical
and show the precise shape that these distributions will take on in the long run.
The easiest case to make this calculation is if we have a uniform distribution,
where each possible face of the die has an equal probability, 1/6.
For example, if you then want to know how likely different sums are for a pair of dice,
it's essentially a counting game,
where you count up how many distinct pairs take on the same sum.
Which in the diagram I've drawn,
you can conveniently think about by going through all of the different diagonals.
Since each such pair has an equal chance of showing up, 1 in 36,
all you have to do is count the sizes of these buckets.
That gives us a definitive shape for the distribution describing a sum of two dice
and if we were to play the same game with all possible triplets,
the resulting distribution would look like this.
Now, what's more challenging but a lot more interesting is to ask what happens
if we have a non-uniform distribution for that single die.
We actually talked all about this in the last video.
You do essentially the same thing, you go through all the distinct
pairs of dice which add up to the same value.
It's just that instead of counting those pairs,
for each pair, you multiply the two probabilities of each particular face coming up
and then you add all those together.
The computation that does this for all possible sums has a fancy name,
it's called a Convolution but it's essentially just the weighted version of the counting game
that anyone who's played with a pair of dice already finds familiar.
For our purposes, in this lesson, I'll have the computer calculate all that,
simply display the results for you and invite you to observe certain patterns,
but under the hood, this is what's going on.
So, just to be crystal clear on what's being represented here,
if you imagine sampling two different values from that top distribution,
the one describing a single die and adding them together,
then the second distribution I'm drawing represents how likely you are to see various different sums.
Likewise, if you imagine sampling three distinct values from that top distribution and adding them together,
the next plot represents the probabilities for various different sums in that case.
So, if I compute what the distributions for these sums look like for larger and larger sums,
well, you know what I'm going to say, it looks more and more like a bell curve.
But before we get to that, I want you to make a couple more simple observations.
For example, these distributions seem to be wandering to the right,
and also they seem to be getting more spread out and a little bit more flat.
You cannot describe the central limit theorem quantitatively without taking into account both of those effects,
which in turn requires describing the mean and the standard deviation.
Maybe you're already familiar with those,
but I want to make minimal assumptions here and it never hurts to review.
So let's quickly go over both of those.
The mean of a distribution, often denoted with a Greek letter, mu,
is a way of capturing the center of mass for that distribution.
It's calculated as the expected value of our random variable,
which is a way of saying you go through all of the different possible outcomes
and you multiply the probability of that outcome times the value of the variable.
If higher values are more probable, that weighted sum is going to be bigger,
if lower values are more probable, that weighted time is going to be smaller.
A little more interesting is if you want to measure how spread out this distribution is,
because there's multiple different ways you might do it.
One of them is called the Variance.
The idea there is to look at the difference between each possible value and the mean,
square that difference and ask for its expected value.
The idea is that whether your value is below or above the mean,
when you square that difference you get a positive number
and the larger the difference, the bigger that number.
Squaring it like this turns out to make the math
much, much nicer than if we did something like an absolute value,
but the downside is that it's hard to think about this as a distance
in our diagram because the units are off.
Kind of like the units here are square units
whereas a distance in our diagram would be a kind of linear unit.
So, another way to measure spread is what's called the Standard Deviation,
which is the square root of this value.
That can be interpreted much more reasonably as a distance on our diagram
and it's commonly denoted with the Greek letter Sigma.
So, you know M for mean, as for standard deviation but both in Greek.
Looking back at our sequence of distributions,
let's talk about the mean and standard deviation.
If we call the mean of the initial distribution mu,
which for the one Illustrated happens to be 2.24,
hopefully, it won't be too surprising if I tell you that the mean of the next one is two times mu.
That is, you roll a pair of dice, you want to know the expected value of the sum,
it's two times the expected value for a single die.
Similarly, the expected value for our sum of size 3 is 3 times mu
and so on and so forth. The mean just marches steadily on to the right,
which is why our distributions seem to be drifting off in that direction.
A little more challenging but very important is to describe how the standard deviation changes.
The key fact here is that if you have two different random variables,
then the variance for the sum of those variables
is the same as just adding together the original two variances.
This is one of those facts that you can just compute when you unpack all the definitions.
There are a couple nice intuitions for why it's true.
My tentative plan is to just actually make a series about probability
and talk about things like intuition's underlying variants and its cousins there,
but right now, the main thing I want you to highlight
is how it's the variance that adds, it's not the standard deviation that adds.
So critically, if you were to take 'n' different realizations of the same random variable
and ask what the sum looks like,
the variance of that sum is 'n' times the variance of your original variable,
meaning the standard deviation, the square root of all this,
is the square root of n times the original standard deviation.
For example, back in our sequence of distributions,
if we label the standard deviation of our initial one with Sigma, then the next standard deviation
is going to be the square root of 2 times Sigma,
and after that, it looks like the square root of 3 times Sigma and so on and so forth.
This like I said is very important.
It means that even though our distributions are getting spread out,
they're not spreading out all that quickly.
They only do so in proportion to the square root of the size of the sum.
As we prepare to make a more quantitative description of the central limit theorem,
the core intuition I want you to keep in your head